Roughly 43,000 years ago,
تقريباً منذ 43,000 سنة،
a young cave bear died in the rolling hills
مات دب كهف صغير في التلال الزالجة
on the northwest border of modern day Slovenia.
في الجانب الشمالي الغربي لسلوفينيا الحديثة.
A thousand years later, a mammoth died in southern Germany.
بعد ألف سنة، مات ماموث في جنوب ألمانيا.
A few centuries after that, a griffon vulture also died
بعد ذلك بقرون قليلة، مات أيضاً نسر صغير
in the same vicinity.
في نفس المنطقة.
And we know almost nothing about how these animals met their deaths,
و نحن لا نعرف شيئ تقريباً عن كيفية موت هذه الحيوانات،
but these different creatures dispersed across both time and space
لكن هذه الحيوانات المختلفة التي تشتتت خلال الزمان والمكان
did share one remarkable fate.
اشتركت في مصير واحد مميز.
After their deaths, a bone from each of their skeletons
بعد موتها، عظمة من الهيكل العظمي لكل منها
was crafted by human hands
صاغتها أيدي الإنسان
into a flute.
الي ناي.
Think about that for a second.
فكر في ذلك لثانية.
Imagine you're a caveman, 40,000 years ago.
تخيّل أنك رجل كهف، منذ 40,000 سنة مضت.
You've mastered fire.
قمت باشعال نار.
You've built simple tools for hunting.
قمت ببناء أدوات بسيطة للصيد.
You've learned how to craft garments from animal skins
تعلمت كيف تصنع ملابساً من جلود الحيوانات
to keep yourself warm in the winter.
لتحافظ علي جسمك دافئاً خلال الشتاء.
What would you choose to invent next?
ماذا كنت لتختار أن تخترع بعد ذلك؟
It seems preposterous that you would invent the flute,
يبدو مثيراً للسخرية أنك كنت ستخترع الناي،
a tool that created useless vibrations in air molecules.
الأداة التي خلقت اهتزازات لا فائدة منها في جزيئات الهواء.
But that is exactly what our ancestors did.
لكن هذا بالضبط هو ما فعله أسلافنا.
Now this turns out to be surprisingly common
الأن، اتضح على نحو مفاجئ أن هذا شيء شائع
in the history of innovation.
في تاريخ الابتكار.
Sometimes people invent things
أحياناً يخترع الناس أشياءً
because they want to stay alive or feed their children
بسبب أنهم يريدون البقاء أحياءً أو إطعام أطفالهم
or conquer the village next door.
أو غزو القرية المجاورة.
But just as often,
لكن كالغالب،
new ideas come into the world
الأفكار الجديدة تأتي الي العالم
simply because they're fun.
ببساطة لأنها ممتعة.
And here's the really strange thing:
و هنا الشئ الغريب فعلاً:
many of those playful but seemingly frivolous inventions
العديد من تلك الاختراعات المرحة لكن والتي تبدو كاختراعات تافهة
ended up sparking momentous transformations
انتهت باشعال شرارة تحولات هامة للغاية
in science, in politics and society.
في العلوم والسياسة والمجتمع.
Take what may be the most important invention of modern times:
اليك ما يمكن أن يكون أكثر الاختراعات أهمية في العصور الحديثة:
programmable computers.
أجهزة الحاسوب القابلة للبرمجة.
Now, the standard story is that computers descend from military technology,
الأن القصة الأساسية هي أن أجهزة الحاسوب تنحدر من التكنولوجيا العسكرية،
since many of the early computers were designed specifically
بما ان العديد من أجهزة الحاسوب الأولى صُممت خصيصاً
to crack wartime codes or calculate rocket trajectories.
لتخترق الشفرات في وقت الحرب أو لحساب مسارات الصواريخ.
But in fact, the origins of the modern computer
لكن في الحقيقة، أصول الحاسوب الحديث
are much more playful,
مرحة أكثر بكثير،
even musical,
أو حتي أكثر موسيقية،
than you might imagine.
مما يمكن أن تتخيل.
The idea behind the flute,
الفكرة وراء الناي،
of just pushing air through tubes to make a sound,
أن تدفع الهواء خلال أنابيب لتصدر صوتاً،
was eventually modified to create the first organ
عُدلت في النهاية وقادت لابتكار أول أورغن
more than 2,000 years ago.
منذ أكثر من 2,000 سنة مضت.
Someone came up with the brilliant idea of triggering sounds
شخصٌ ما أتى بالفكرة الرائعة الخاصة باثارة الأصوات
by pressing small levers with our fingers,
بالضغط علي مقابض صغيرة بأصابعنا،
inventing the first musical keyboard.
مخترعاً لوحة المفاتيح الموسيقية الأولي.
Now, keyboards evolved from organs to clavichords to harpsichords
الأن، تطورت لوحة المفاتيح من الأورغن الي موترة المفاتيح إلي البيان القيثاري
to the piano,
إلي البيانو،
until the middle of the 19th century,
حتي منتصف القرن التاسع عشر،
when a bunch of inventors finally hit on the idea
عندما أتي أخيراً مجموعة من المخترعين بفكرة
of using a keyboard to trigger not sounds but letters.
استخدام لوحة المفاتيح لإثارة ليس أصوات لكن حروف.
In fact, the very first typewriter
في الحقيقة، أول ألة كاتبة
was originally called "the writing harpsichord."
كانت بالأصل تُدعي "البيان القيثاري الكاتبة."
Flutes and music led to even more powerful breakthroughs.
ألات الناي والموسيقي أدّت إلي اختراقات أقوي.
About a thousand years ago,
منذ تقريباً ألف سنة مضت،
at the height of the Islamic Renaissance,
في أوج النهضة الإسلامية،
three brothers in Baghdad designed a device
ثلاثة إخوة في بغداد صمموا جهازاً
that was an automated organ.
والذي كان أورغناً آلياً.
They called it "the instrument that plays itself."
سموه "الألة التي تعزف بمفردها."
Now, the instrument was basically a giant music box.
الأن، الألة في الأساس كانت صندوق موسيقي ضخم.
The organ could be trained to play various songs by using instructions
يمكن أن يتم تدريب الأرغن ليعزف أغاني متنوعة باستخدام تعليمات
encoded by placing pins on a rotating cylinder.
يتم تشفيرها بوضع دبابيس علي أسطوانة دوارة.
And if you wanted the machine to play a different song,
و اذا أردت الألة أن تعزف أغنية مختلفة،
you just swapped a new cylinder in with a different code on it.
تقوم بالتبديل بادخال أسطوانة جديدة بشفرة مختلفة عليها.
This instrument was the first of its kind.
هذه الألة كانت الأولى من نوعها.
It was programmable.
كانت قابلة للبرمجة.
Now, conceptually, this was a massive leap forward.
الأن، من حيث المفهوم، كانت هذه قفزةً عملاقةً للأمام.
The whole idea of hardware and software
الفكرة الكلية للأجزاء الصلبة والبرمجيات
becomes thinkable for the first time with this invention.
أصبحت ممكنة للتفكير بها لأول مرة مع هذا الاختراع.
And that incredibly powerful concept
و ذلك المفهوم القوي الذي لا يصدق
didn't come to us as an instrument of war or of conquest,
لم يأت إلينا كآلة للحرب أو الغزو،
or necessity at all.
أو للضرورة علي الإطلاق.
It came from the strange delight of watching a machine play music.
أتي من المتعة الغريبة لمشاهدة آلة تعزف الموسيقي.
In fact, the idea of programmable machines
في الحقيقة، فكرة الألات القابلة للبرمجة
was exclusively kept alive by music for about 700 years.
بقيت حيّة حصرياً علي الموسيقي لحوالي 700 سنة.
In the 1700s, music-making machines
في فترة 1700، الألات الصانعة للموسيقي
became the playthings of the Parisian elite.
أصبحت ألعوبة النخبة الباريسيين.
Showmen used the same coded cylinders
استخدم رجال العروض نفس الاسطوانات المشفرة
to control the physical movements of what were called automata,
ليتحكموا بالحركات الجسمانية التي سُميت الألية،
an early kind of robot.
نوع قديم من الإنسان الألي.
One of the most famous of those robots
أحد أشهر هؤلاء الرجال الآليين
was, you guessed it, an automated flute player
كان، أنت خمنتها، عازف ناي آلي
designed by a brilliant French inventor
صممه مخترع فرنسي بارع
named Jacques de Vaucanson.
اسمه (جاك دو فوكانسون).
And as de Vaucanson was designing his robot musician,
و كما كان (دو فوكانسون) يصمم إنسانه الألي الموسيقي،
he had another idea.
كانت لديه فكرةٌ أخرى.
If you could program a machine to make pleasing sounds,
إذا تمكنت من برمجة آلة لتصنع أصواتً ممتعة،
why not program it to weave delightful patterns of color out of cloth?
لم لا تبرمجها لنسج أنماط مبهجة من الألوان من الملابس؟
Instead of using the pins of the cylinder to represent musical notes,
بدلاً من استخدام دبابيس الإسطوانة لتمثل حروف موسيقية،
they would represent threads with different colors.
سوف تمثل خيوطاً بألوان مختلفة.
If you wanted a new pattern for your fabric,
إذا ما أردت نمطاً جديداً لقماشك،
you just programmed a new cylinder.
فقط تقوم ببرمجة إسطوانة جديدة.
This was the first programmable loom.
كان هذا أول نول قابل للبرمجة.
Now, the cylinders were too expensive and time-consuming to make,
الأن، كانت الإسطوانات غاليةً للغاية و تستهلك وقتاً كبيراً لصنعها،
but a half century later,
لكن بعد ذلك بنصف قرن،
another French inventor named Jacquard
أتى مخترع فرنسي أخر يُدعي (جاكوارد)
hit upon the brilliant idea of using paper-punched cards
بالفكرة الرائعة وهي استخدام بطاقات مثقّبة ورقية
instead of metal cylinders.
بدلاً من الإسطوانات المعدنية.
Paper turned out to be much cheaper and more flexible
اتضح أن الورق أرخص وأكثر مرونة
as a way of programming the device.
كطريقة لبرمجة الجهاز.
That punch card system inspired Victorian inventor Charles Babbage
ألهم نظام البطاقة المُثقبة المخترع الفيكتوري (تشارل باباج)
to create his analytical engine,
ليبتكر المحرك التحليلي الخاص به،
the first true programmable computer
أول حاسوب حقيقي قابل للبرمجة
ever designed.
تم تصميمه من قبل.
And punch cards were used by computer programmers
كما استخدم مبرمجو الحاسوب البطاقات المُثقّبة
as late as the 1970s.
في أواخر حقبة 1970.
So ask yourself this question:
لذا اسأل نفسك هذا السؤال:
what really made the modern computer possible?
ما الذي جعل جهاز الحاسوب الحديث ممكناً حقاً؟
Yes, the military involvement is an important part of the story,
نعم، المشاركة العسكرية جزء مهم من القصة،
but inventing a computer also required other building blocks:
لكن اختراع حاسوب تطلَب أيضاً قوالب بناء أخرى:
music boxes,
صناديق الموسيقي،
toy robot flute players,
لعبة عازف الناي الألي،
harpsichord keyboards,
ألواح مفاتيح بيان القيثاري،
colorful patterns woven into fabric,
أنماط ملونة منسوجة في شكل قماش،
and that's just a small part of the story.
و ذلك جزء صغير من القصة.
There's a long list of world-changing ideas and technologies
هنالك قائمة طويلة للتكنولوجيا والأفكار التي غيّرت العالم
that came out of play:
التي خرجت من لعب:
public museums, rubber,
المتاحف الشعبية، المطاط،
probability theory, the insurance business
نظرية الإحتمالات، أعمال التأمين
and many more.
و المزيد غيرها.
Necessity isn't always the mother of invention.
الضرورة ليست دائماً أم الاختراع.
The playful state of mind is fundamentally exploratory,
الحالة الذهنية المرحة هي استكشافية على نحو أساسي،
seeking out new possibilities in the world around us.
السعي إلي احتمالات جديدة في العالم من حولنا.
And that seeking is why so many experiences
و هذا السعي هو سبب العديد من التجارب
that started with simple delight and amusement
التي بدأت بمرح بسيط وتسلية
eventually led us to profound breakthroughs.
قادتنا في النهاية إلي اختراقات عميقة.
Now, I think this has implications for how we teach kids in school
الأن، أنا أعتقد أن هذا له تأثير على كيفية تعليمنا للأطفال في المدارس
and how we encourage innovation in our workspaces,
و كيفية تشجيعنا للابتكار في أماكن عملنا،
but thinking about play and delight this way
لكن التفكير في اللعب والمرح بهذه الطريقة
also helps us detect what's coming next.
يساعدنا أيضاً علي الكشف عما هو قادم بعد ذلك.
Think about it: if you were sitting there in 1750
فكر في ذلك: إذا ما كنت هناك في حقبة 1750
trying to figure out the big changes coming to society
تحاول اكتشاف التغييرات الكبيرة القادمة للمجتمع
in the 19th, the 20th centuries,
في القرنين التاسع عشر والعشرين،
automated machines, computers,
الماكينات الألية، أجهزة الحاسوب،
artificial intelligence,
الذكاء الاصطناعي،
a programmable flute
ناي قابل للبرمجة
entertaining the Parisian elite
تسلية النخبة الباريسية
would have been as powerful a clue as anything else at the time.
كانت لتكون فكرة قوية كأي شئ آخر في ذلك الوقت.
It seemed like an amusement at best,
تبدو كتسلية في أحسن الأحوال،
not useful in any serious way,
ليست مفيدة بأي شكل جاد،
but it turned out to be the beginning of a tech revolution
لكن اتضح أنها البداية لثورة تكنولوجية
that would change the world.
ستغيّر العالم.
You'll find the future
سوف تجد المستقبل
wherever people are having the most fun.
أينما وجد الناس أقصى متعة .